A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Program Division, Office Files of Chika A. Iritani FA1479
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Program Division, Office Files of Chika A. Iritani
1987-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Iritani, Chika A.
Ford Foundation
FA1479
1.14 Cubic Feet About 3 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necesary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:069.
Arrangement
Collection consists of two series: chronological files and Ford Foundation Program Review reports.
Original order was maintained during processing.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
1. Chronological files, 1987-1991
2. Program reviews, 1992
Other Finding Aids
Other Finding Aids for collections holding records created by Chika A. Iritani include:
FA528 Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Ford Foundation staff member Chika A. Iritani. The files were created during the time that Iritani served in the foundation's Program Division.
The collection consists of two series. The first series contains a set of chronological files Iritani created to organize her correspondence. This series continues the run of Iritani's chronological files found in Series IV of the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files (FA528) collection. Iritani was not placed in the Developing Countries Program when she created several of the files found in the collection. Letters from February 1990 show a shift in Iritani's position title from Program Division, Developing Countries Program to just Program Division. Therefore, it was decided during processing to keep the records as a separate collection.
The second series contains a group of Program Review reports for different Ford Foundation Developing Country Program's regional and country initiatives.
Biographical / Historical
Chika A. Iritani supported the Ford Foundation's grants administration activities for many years while she worked in the foundation's Program Division.
Iritani passed away in 1997.
Ford Foundation; Program budgeting
- Chronological files, 1987-1991; 1; .76 Cubic Feet About 2 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains a set of chronological files Ford Foundation staff member Chika A. Iritani created to organize her correspondence. Most files primarily consist of correspondence addressed from Iritani to grantees and other Ford staff members. However, the 1987-1990 Chronological file (Box 2, Folders 8-10) also includes a significant amount of correspondence addressed to Iritani. Correspondence in that file includes many faxes and telegrams and originates from a more extensive period of time than what is covered by the other chronological files.
  Correspondence in the series generally regards the receipt of grant reports, closeouts of grants, purchase orders, and program reviews among other grants administration and program management activities.
  Series continues the run of Iritani chronological files started in Series IV of the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files (FA528) collection.
  - Chronological file, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Chronological file, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Chronological file, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Chronological file, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - Chronological file, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Program reviews, 1992; 2; .38 Cubic Feet 1 LTR size Hollinger box
  Series contains a group of Ford Foundation Program Review reports published in May 1992. The reports analyze different Ford Foundation Developing Country Program's regional and country initiatives.
  - Program Review: Bangladesh (Dhaka, Bangladesh), 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Program Review: West Africa (Dakar, Senegal), 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Program Review: Eastern and Southern Africa (Nairobi, Kenya), 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Program Review: Africa Regional, 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Program Review: Israel, 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Program Review: Middle East and North Africa (Cairo, Egypt), 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Program Review: Beijing, 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 20)